Ivan Brugere

AI Research Scientist

ivan@ivanbrugere.com 🗘 ivanbrugere

Current Objective

I am an AI Research Scientist with experience in interdisciplinary biological sciences and spatiotemporal applications. My core interest is in machine learning on graphs/networks. My most recent work has been in fairness and bias, particularly within complex, graph-structured data. My PhD (defended 2020) focused on data science methodologies for inferring and validating graphs derived from underlying data, with applications in social networks, mobile location privacy, and large-scale multimedia recommendation.

Experience

Mar. 2021- **JPMorgan Chase & Co.** AI Research Scientist

Working on ML fairness in graph-structured environments, multi-sided marketplaces, and AutoML platforms.

Salesforce Research Research Scientist - AI For Good

Worked with several Salesforce non-profit customers and external collaborators. Focused on projects relating to fairness and bias, particularly in AutoML platforms, and novel, structured environments such as graphs/networks.

Summer 2018 Amazon Applied Scientist Intern (Mentor: Alex Smola)

Designed deep learning graph APIs on MXNet. Focused on structured computational models on graphs, and scalability. Part of the Amazon Web Services AI Platforms team.

Summer 2015 Microsoft Data Science Intern (Mentor: Marcello Hasegawa)

Developed textual and device models for novelty detection and attribution in the Windows 10 user population.

Summer 2014 Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory Research Intern (Mentor: Brian Gallagher)

Formulated graph inference problems over several scientific research domains.

University of Illinois at Chicago Research Fellow (Mentor: Prof. Venkat Venkatakrishnan)

Graph-based models for attribute inference and privacy preservation on real mobile device datasets.

Summer 2013 Technicolor Research Research Intern (Mentor: Fernando Silveira)

Rule discovery for biometric sensor time series data for actionable analysis of film audiences. Developed methods to discover and visualize dynamic audience communities.

2012-2017 University of Illinois at Chicago Research Assistant (Advisor: Prof. Tanya Berger-Wolf)

Model selection for graph structure inference and prediction. Focusing on ecology and populations biology domains.

2010-2012 University of Minnesota Research Assistant (Advisor: Prof. Vipin Kumar)

Time series change detection and anomaly detection on large remote sensing datasets. Focused on incorporating spatial aspects for

 $change\ significance\ testing, and\ domain-driven\ information\ retrieval.$

2002-2003 University of Minnesota Web Applications Developer (College of Liberal Arts)

Education

2013-2015

2012-2020 University of Illinois at Chicago Computer Science PhD (Advisor: Prof. Tanya Berger-Wolf)

University of Minnesota Web Applications Developer (Department of Computer Science)

Thesis: Network Structure Inference: Methodology and Applications.

2009-2012 University of Minnesota Computer Science M.S. (Advisor: Prof. Vipin Kumar)

Thesis: Approximate Search on Massive Spatiotemporal Datasets.

2007-2009 The New School International Affairs M.A

2002-2007 University of Minnesota Computer Science B.S., Cultural Studies and Comparative Literature B.A.

Publications

GAEA: Graph Augmentation for Equitable Access via Reinforcement Learning G.S. Ramachandran, I. Brugere, L.R. Varshney, C. Xiong

(AAAI AIES 2021

Evaluation of crowdsourced mortality prediction models as a framework for assessing AI in medicine T. Bergquist, T. Schaffter, Y. Yan,

T. Yu, I. Brugere et al. (Medrxiv preprint)

Continuously Benchmarked Crowdsourced Challenge for COVID-19 Outcome Prediction Y. Yan, T. Schaffter, T. Bergquist, T. Yu, J.

Prosser, Z. Aydin, A. Jabeer, I. Brugere, et al. (In ${\it Submission})$

Network Structure Inference: Methodology and Applications

I. Brugere (PhD Thesis)

Network Structure Inference, A Survey: Motivations, Methods, and Applications

I. Brugere, B. Gallagher, T. Y. Berger-Wolf (ACM Computing Surveys)

Network model selection with task-focused minimum description length $% \left(1\right) =\left(1\right) \left(1\right$

I. Brugere, T.Y. Berger-Wolf (WWW BigNet Workshop on Learning Representations for Big Networks)

Coordination Event Detection and Initiator Identification in Time Series Data

C. Amornbunchornvej, I. Brugere, A. Strandburg-Peshkin, D. Farine, M.C. Crofoot, T.Y. Berger-Wolf (ACM TKDD)

2017 Evaluating Social Networks Using Task-Focused Network Inference

I. Brugere, C. Kanich, T.Y. Berger-Wolf (SIGKDD MLG Workshop on Mining and Learning in Graphs)

A General Framework for Task-Oriented Network Inference

I. Brugere, C. Kanich, T.Y. Berger-Wolf (SIAM SDM Workshop on Inferring Networks from Non-Network Data)

Both Nearest Neighbours and Long-term Affiliates Predict Individual Locations During Collective Movement in Wild Baboons

D. Farine, A. Strandburg-Peshkin, T.Y. Berger-Wolf, B. Ziebart, I. Brugere, J. Li, M. Crofoot (Nature Scientific Reports)

2015 Social Information Improves Location Prediction in the Wild

J. Li, I. Brugere, B. Ziebart, T. Y. Berger-Wolf, M. Crofoot, D. Farine (AAAI Workshop on Trajectory-based Behaviour Analytics)

Modeling and Analysis of Spatiotemporal Social Networks 2014

I. Brugere, V. M.V. Gunturi, and S. Shekhar (Encyclopedia of Social Network Analysis and Mining)

Approximate Search on Massive Spatiotemporal Datasets 2012

I. Brugere, K. Steinhaeuser, S. Boriah, and V. Kumar (IEEE ICDM Workshop on Spatial and Spatiotemporal Data Mining SSTDM)

2011 Incorporating Natural Variation into Time Series-Based Land Cover Change Identification

V. Mithal, A. Garg, I. Brugere, S. Boriah, V. Kumar, M. Steinbach, C. Potter, and S. Klooster (NASA Conference on Intelligent Data

A Study of Time Series Noise Reduction Techniques in the Context of Land Cover Change Detection

X. Chen, V. Mithal, S.R. Vangala, I. Brugere, S. Boriah, and V. Kumar (NASA Conference on Intelligent Data Understanding)

A Novel Time Series Based Approach to Detect Gradual Vegetation Changes in Forests

Y. Chamber, A. Garg, V. Mithal, I. Brugere, M. Lau, V. Krishna, S. Boriah, M. Steinbach, V. Kumar, C. Potter, and S. Klooster (NASA

Conference on Intelligent Data Understanding)

GOPHER: Global Observation of Planetary Health and Ecosystem Resources

A. Garg, V. Mithal, Y. Chamber, I. Brugere, V. Chaudhari, M. Dunham, V. Krishna, S. Krishnamurthy, S. Vangala, S. Boriah, M.

Steinbach, V. Kumar, A. Cho, JD Stanley, T. Abraham, J. C. Castilla-Rubio, C. Potter, and S.A. Klooster (IEEE Geoscience and Remote

Sensing Symposium IGARSS)

Scholarships and Awards

Scholarships 2014-2016 NSF IGERT Electronic Security and Privacy Fellowship

> 2014-2016 University of Illinois at Chicago, Chancellor's Graduate Research Fellowship

2014 Google Lime Scholarship

Awards 2017 IEEE ICDM Travel Award

SIAM SDM Travel Award

ACM Tapia Celebration of Diversity in Computing, Travel Award 2016

ACM SIGKDD Broadening Participation in Data Mining Travel Award

ACM WSDM Travel Award

IEEE ICDM Travel Award 2015

> ACM Ubicomp Broadening Participation Travel Award ACM SIGKDD Ram Kumar Memorial Travel Award

SIAM CSE Travel Award supported by the Sustainable Horizons Institute Fifty for the Future Award supported by the Illinois

Technology Foundation

ACM BCB Travel Award 2014

ACM SIGKDD Broadening Participation in Data Mining Travel Award

ACM Tapia Celebration of Diversity in Computing, Travel Award

Service

Tutorials 2018 Modeling Data with Networks + Network Embedding: Problems, Methodologies and Frontiers

I. Brugere, B. Perozzi, P. Cui, W. Zhu, J. Pei, T.Y. Berger-Wolf (KDD 2018)

PhD Forum (IEEE ICDM'19) Workshops 2019

> NetInf'17: First Workshop on Inferring Networks from Non-Network Data (SIAM SDM'17) 2017

Inferring Networks from Non-Network Data (SIAM AM'16) 2016

AAAI, KDD, SDM, WWW Program Committees 2021

> AAAI, ICDM, KDD, SDM, WWW 2020 AAAI, CIKM, ICDM, KDD, SDM 2019

KDD 2018

AAAI, CIKM, ICDM, IJCAI, KDD, PAKDD, SDM, WWW (Conference) Reviewer

ACM CSUR, IMS AOAS, IEEE TKDE, KAIS (Journal)

Community ACM Tapia Celebration of Diversity in Computing 2020 Accessibility Committee Bloomberg Data For Good Exchange Program

Google Lime campus ambassador

University of Washington-AccessSTEM volunteer

ACM SIGKDD Broadening Participation in Data Mining Coordinator, Mentoring Co-Chair (2014, 2016, 2017)

Teaching and Notable Courses Teaching Assistant: Computer Algorithms I (Senior-level)

Advanced Computational Biology and Bioinformatics Seminar

Advanced Data Mining Seminar

Field Course in Computational Ecology at Mpala Research Centre, Kenya

✓ ivan@ivanbrugere.com♠ ivanbrugere

in LinkedIn

¶ Google scholar

ORCiD